Finding Aid for Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation (University of Michigan) records, 1957-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation (University of Michigan) records 1957-1961 1958, 1961
University of Michigan. Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation.
.5 linear ft.
87109 Bimu B3 2
The Commission on Year-Round Integration Records contain correspondence, reports, and background materials of the Commission, and its predecessor unit, the Calendar Study Committee.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated to the Bentley Historical Library. Donor number unknown.
The record group is open for research.
On February 27, 1961 University of Michigan President Harlan Hatcher appointed an eight member commission "to consider possible plans for integrated year-round operation and to recommend to him that program which would be best suited to the present and future needs of the University." ( Box 1, folder: Final Report )
The commission examined three basic questions: 1.) Was a basic change to the University's academic routine justified and desirable? 2.) What alternative arrangements provided year-round integrated operation while maintaining the standards of the university? 3.) What arrangements should be recommended to the President and the Regents?
The work of the Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation (CYRIO) was very much a continuation of several earlier calendar committees. Among its predecessors was the University Calendar Study Committee, chaired by Professor Paul S. Dwyer of the Mathematics department, which reported its findings June 19, 1958. Appointed by President Hatcher on January 9, 1958, this five member committee had as its major goal "making recommendations for a university calendar suited to the times." (Box 1, folder: Final Report, June 19, 1958) The committee made many recommendations regarding all facets of the university calendar, from the scheduling of new student orientation to the scheduling of commencement. According to the CYRIO report, the Dwyer Report was "a major guide to other colleges and universities in their deliberations."
Based on its research, the CYRIO recommended that year-round operation was necessary and desirable.
The records of the Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation are comprised of two series: The Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation (CYRIO), and the Calendar Study Committee (the "Dwyer Committee").
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Calendar Study Committee.; University of Michigan--Calendars.; University of Michigan. Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation.
- Commission on Year-Round Integrated Operation, 1961
  The CYRIO series includes some Dwyer Committee records, an incomplete set of meeting minutes and materials from the Pittsburgh Conference on Year-Round Operation. Although the records in the series are somewhat sparse, the inclusion of the commission's final report fills in many of the gaps in the record.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes (Box 1)
  - LS&A Examination Problem, Calendar Committee (Box 1)
  - Pittsburgh Conference on Year-Round Operation (Box 1)
  - Scheduling Classes (Rutgers, Penn State) (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Final Report, one bound volume (Box 1)
  - Calendar Study Committee, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Calendar Study Committee Chronology, 1958 (Box 1)
- Calendar Study Committee, 1958
  The Calendar Study Committee series is comprised of correspondence and reports that the committee used and generated, including its final report, as well as sample calendars that were considered. Also included are the reactions of deans, department heads, committees and the campus at large.
  - Material on Calendar (Box 1)
  - Elements of a University Calendar (Box 1)
  - Sample Calendars (Box 1)
  - Comments on preliminary report (Box 1)
  - Examinations (Box 1)
  - Deans, Department Heads and Committees (Box 1)
  - Campus reaction (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate athletics (impact) (Box 1)
  - Wayne State report (Box 1)
  - News items (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
  - Final report, June 19, 1958, one bound volume (Box 1)